[Music]
what's the effect of nutrition on
periodontal disease periodontal disease
is a bacterial infection that results in
inflammatory destruction of the
connective tissue and bone that supports
the teeth is therefore one of the
leading causes of our teeth falling out
like most infections though how our body
responds may play a critical role yes
the presence of bacteria is the primary
cause but a susceptible host is also
necessary for disease initiation the
standard explanation of parodontal
disease is the plaque Theory the buildup
of plaque leads to gingivitis gum
inflammation which leads to
periodontitis inflammation lowered down
beneath the gums but in some forms of
parodontal disease plaque doesn't appear
to play a critical role therefore in the
last few years there's been more
interest in the importance of systemic
Health our body's response in this
respect nutrition may be of great
importance since it's been implicated in
a number of other inflammatory diseases
all of which carry elevated perodontal
disease risk traditionally when we think
of the effects of nutrition on Dental
diseases we only think about cavities uh
however there's been less research on
the role of diet in periodontal diseases
well if it's about inflammation one
would expect saturative fatr diets to
make things worse increasing oxidative
stress as well as inflammation uh so we
may want to cut down unsaturated fat but
look let's not just speculate I mean is
there an association between cholesterol
levels and periodontitis if not it would
be hard to implicate saturated fat but
no there does appear to be a link those
with high cholesterol do appear to have
up to double the risk what about
perodontal conditions in vegetarians 100
vegetarians versus non-vegetarians were
studied and those eating vegetarian did
have better parodontal conditions less
inflammation signs less parodontal
damage and better Dental Home Care
however it should be considered that
vegetarians may not just be avoiding
meat but are healthier in other ways
like better Dental home care but do
people who eat more saturated fat get
more
periodontitis yeah about double the risk
of the highest levels of intake and this
study was in Japan where they eat less
than half the meat and dairy compared to
the US the only way to know for sure
though is to do an Interventional trial
where you change people's diets and see
what happens in other words you have to
put it to the test and bone loss was
indeed magnified by a diet high and
saturated fat and cholesterol but if
you're thinking H that's a weird looking
jaw that's because it was a study done
on
brats this is what I was looking for
though the title kind of ruins the
suspense a high fiber lowfat diet
improves parodontal disease markers in
terms of probing depth clinical
attachment loss and bleeding on probing
all the standard measures and of course
eating healthier diet body weight blood
sugar control and systemic inflammation
improved as well ah but that complicates
things I mean maybe their mouths got
better just because they lost so much
weight you can improve parodontal
disease with just bariatric surgery like
stomach stapling well after 8 weeks on
the diet they went back on their regular
diet and so gained most of the weight
back but the parodontal disease
improvements persisted suggesting it was
more than just a weight loss that led to
the improvements they're thinking maybe
the high-fiber diet altered their good
gut Flora or maybe their oral Flora what
exactly was going on well German
researchers took 20 women with mild
moderate chronic parodontitis and for a
year tried to transition their diets
towards more wholesome nutrition meaning
more plant Foods more Whole Foods more
Fresh Foods trying to Center their diets
around vegetables and fruit whole grains
potatoes and legumes beans splies chick
bees and lentils and after 12 months the
patient showed a significant reduction
of probing pocket depth gingerful
inflammation and measure for the first
time decreased concentrations of
inflammatory chemicals inside the
crevice between the tooth and gums uh
which are thought responsible for the
tissue destruction in perodontal disease
a decrease by as much as 75% and all the
while their oral hygiene status didn't
change suggesting it was the diet that
did
it but what was missing here a control
group there's never been any randomized
double blind but control trials have
died for periodontal disease um until
now which we'll cover next
[Music]